<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Çağıl Gümüş Blog</title><link href="https://cagil-gumus.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://cagil-gumus.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://cagil-gumus.github.io/</id><updated>2025-04-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>How to do science with FPGAs.</title><link href="https://cagil-gumus.github.io/how-to-fpga-science.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-04-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-04-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Çağıl Gümüş</name></author><id>tag:cagil-gumus.github.io,2025-04-27:/how-to-fpga-science.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Talking about how FPGAs are used inside experimental physics projects.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;!-- Humanity has been accelerating a charged particle is happening since a very long time.

You can do many cool things with an accelerated, properly shaped particle beams. You can:

* mash them together, 
* literally target them to your skull so it deposits its energy on top of the cancerious cells 
* bombard the nuclear power plant waste with it and reduce its decay half-time 
* wiggle them and turn them into a photon particles! 

Where I work, we tend to convert them into a very bright, and very coherent light sources. Scientist then takes these photons and do experiment with it. I have zero clue about what's happening on the other side. At work, I usually focus my attention that this photon light is proper and arrives to its destination (what we call usually experiment hutches) correctly.

Now, it's pretty obviously FPGAs are all over the place here. It's fantastic platform for people to write code that can react in nano seconds. It's used as fast-feedback systems, data acquisition systems, machine/personel protection, and so on. However, Let's pick one and talk about it: 

FPGA Based Low-Level RF Controller 

The acceleration of any charged particle is usually achieved with High Power Radio Frequency waves. These waves are driven into a superconducting cavity. These cavities shaped in a that only one fundamental frequency (and it's harmanics) can be excited. 

The role of the FPGAs are the keep these RF waves stable in amplitude and phase. In order to achieve this, FPGA needs to do two things: 

* Understand what's happening inside the cavity 
* Influence what's inside the cavity 

So basically, close a feedback loop. The analog RF signal has to be digitized with an ADC  --&gt;</content><category term="FPGA"></category></entry><entry><title>What is my taste?</title><link href="https://cagil-gumus.github.io/music-test.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-04-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-04-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Çağıl Gümüş</name></author><id>tag:cagil-gumus.github.io,2025-04-27:/music-test.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Talking about music stuff&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html"></content><category term="Music"></category></entry></feed>